Now.
The game is pretty fun, there's no doubt about that.
But we can't lie to ourselves and say it's very challenging because it's not really that tricky.
Our ball pretty much just stays at a constant speed and the game difficulty is always the same.
So where's the fun in that?
So let's see how we can add a bit of a challenge to our game by making levels of increasing difficulty.
Now essentially what we want to happen is to have our ball continuously increase in speed as our score
increases.
Now this is where you'll start to see the true power of variables, as we're going to use them to change
the whole dynamic of our game and our code.
If you take a look at what is actually dictating the speed of our ball, you will see it is just this
move ten steps block.
So if we increase this number to say 15 and then hit play again.
Now.
Just now how the ball's going a lot faster.
So what this means is to increase the difficulty of our game, we need to increase the number here.
And obviously we don't want to sit here and do it manually.
So let's get the variables to do the work for us.
So moving over back to our variables, let's create a new one.
This time we call it ball speed.
And again we can make this a local variable by clicking here.
Now, as you can see, our new variable appears right on our screen.
But unlike school, our player doesn't actually need to see this number.
But we can leave it here for now while we edit the code to make sure it's doing the right thing.
So now that we have our ball speed variable, you will see that we can actually drag this block here
and onto our scripting area.
And as you should notice, this block is the same shape as this one here.
So we can simply drag our variable into our move steps block.
Unfortunately, you also noticed that, well, the game doesn't really do anything and well, it shouldn't,
because if you look at the code, we are moving ball speed steps and the ball speed variable is zero.
And so we are moving zero steps.
So quick fix to this is setting the ball speed to ten when the game starts, which is the same speed
as it was.
And once again by clicking play you will see the game is back in working order.
But now we are just back to square one.
However, now we want our game to increase in difficulty as we play.
So at this stage, if you look down at your keyboard, you will see a long bar called the spacebar and
if you click on this what it will do, it is going to pause this video.
But before you do that, this will give you an opportunity to work out how to add this feature on your
own and develop your problem solving skills.
So click the spacebar to pause this video and try to see if you can solve this problem.
I'll suggest creating a new script, but I'll be waiting on the other side of this.
Pause and see if you can get this now to work.
Did you figure it out?
As I mentioned, there are often a bunch of ways we can implement new features, but the simplest solution
is often the best solution.
So let's create a new script that controls our game difficulty.
As always, we need this block here.
Then we need this change variable by block here and ensure it is ball speed selected.
And now we need a way to have this continually increase.
Quite simply we can do this by grabbing a forever or a repeat loop.
And either one will allow us to constantly refresh the game difficulty.
In our case, I'm going to use a repeat block because we don't want the game to just keep getting more
and more difficult to a point of impossibility.
So let's put this block in this one, and I'm sure you can guess what will happen when we start the
game.
Yeah, our ball just goes straight to max speed.
Well, thankfully there's an easy solution is to drag in this white block.
And then let's set it to five seconds.
And now when we play again you can see that our game.
Slowly.
But surely starts to gain in difficulty as time passes.
And eventually gets the point where becomes near impossible.
So this script might need a bit of tweaking, but we'll leave you to do that.
What we can also do now that our difficulty variable here has been added properly to our game, is we
can hide it from our screen simply by unchecking this box as is.
No real need for the players to see it.
And well, that's about it for now.
We have completed stage two and develop the gameplay mechanics right now to the last stage, which is
kind of the fun stage where we polish up our game and add in some nice looking graphics and some sound
and even animation.